
Introduction

This is a very basic guide to network operation. It will help us to understand later on how to configure our ParrotSec OS system. In the future you, reader, are expected to investigate and study on your own (much more).

Currently, many of the devices around us are connected to the Internet or at least to our home or office network. Our SmartTV, mobile phones, smartwatches, tablets, PC, coffee maker (?),...

For this reason, it is important to know in broad terms how our networks work, which means all those acronyms and words that ask us when we have to configure our devices.

IP Address

In this document we will deal with version 4 of IP (IPv4), although version 6 (IPv6) is becoming more widespread. Despite this increase in the number of IPv6 configurations, this configuration is not yet common in our homes so we will try to explain IPv4.

All systems that need to communicate with each other must have an IP address. This address must be unique and cannot be repeated on the same network. If this happens, both devices will be cancelled until the dispute is resolved.

An IP address (v4) consists of four blocks of decimal numbers, separated by dots. Each number block can go from 0 to 255.

Examples:

	* 192.168.0.1
	* 1.2.3.4
	* 195.255.1.37

I will give an example to try to explain this (the data is invented and I will put it only as an example). Let's say our home router, our PC, a printer and our favorite internet page.

	PC, printer, router: Private ip are available (belonging to our home network)
	Router, WEB Page: They have public ip (need a public ip to communicate)

You can see that the router maintains two IP addresses: a public one to access the external services provided by the Internet, and a private one to interconnect with the systems of our home network.

	Public IP
	----------------------------------
	WEB page: 	104.24.124.114
	Router: 		85.83.4.127
	
	
	Private IP
	----------------------------------
	Router: 		192.168.0.1
	PC: 		192.168.0.10
	Printer:  		192.168.0.12

We could make an analogy between what was shown above and the telephone system. All phone numbers are different (public IP), but we have switchboards (routers) that are capable of routing a call (routing) to different extensions (private IP). These extensions, looking only at them, can be repeated in different companies or households.

Netmask

The network mask is used on private networks to indicate the range of a subnet.

Private IP addresses must be within the ranges listed below:

	From 10.0.0.0 to 10.255.255.255
	From 172.16.0.0 to 172.31.255.255
	From 192.168.0.0 to 192.168.255.255

The following IPs should not be configured manually:

169.254.0.0 a 169.254.255.255 
224.0.0.0 to 224.0.0.255
224.0.1.0 to 224.0.1.255
224.0.2.0 to 224.0.255.255
224.3.0.0 to 224.4.255.255
232.0.0.0 to 232.255.255.255
233.0.0.0 to 233.255.255.255
233.252.0.0 to 233.255.255.255
234.0.0.0 to 234.255.255.255
239.0.0.0 to 239.255.255.255

Any other IP address will be considered Public. Public IP addresses will generally be assigned by our Internet service provider, so we won't have to worry about them (at least not at the moment).

Look again at the range of private IP addresses. As we have indicated, the network mask specifies the subnet to which a system belongs. In other words, with this value we indicate to our team if it should send a data (package) to a device of our subnet or not. In other words, given an IP address and a network mask, we know that part of that IP address is the value of the subnet and what the host number is. With the mask we also indicate the maximum number of hosts that can be configured in a subnet. Another way to indicate the mask is with your CIDR

Table of possible masks:

	Decimal 	CIDR 	Nº hosts
	--------------- ----	--------
	255.255.255.255	/32
	255.255.255.254	/31
	255.255.255.252	/30 	2
	255.255.255.248	/29 	6
	255.255.255.240	/28 	14
	255.255.255.224	/27 	30
	255.255.255.192	/26 	62
	255.255.255.128	/25 	126
	255.255.255.0 	/24 	254 	
	255.255.254.0 	/23 	510
	255.255.252.0 	/22 	1022
	255.255.248.0 	/21 	2046
	255.255.240.0 	/20 	4094
	255.255.224.0 	/19 	8190
	255.255.192.0 	/18 	16382
	255.255.128.0 	/17 	32766
	255.255.0.0 	/16 	65534 	
	255.254.0.0 	/15 	131070
	255.252.0.0 	/14 	262142
	255.248.0.0 	/13 	524286
	255.240.0.0 	/12 	1048574
	255.224.0.0 	/11 	2097150
	255.192.0.0 	/10 	4194302
	255.128.0.0 	/9 	8388606
	255.0.0.0 	/8 	16777214 	
	254.0.0.0 	/7 	33554430
	252.0.0.0 	/6 	67108862
	248.0.0.0 	/5 	134217726
	240.0.0.0	/4 	268435454
	224.0.0.0 	/3 	536870910
	192.0.0.0 	/2 	1073741822
	128.0.0.0 	/1 	2147483646
	0.0.0.0 	/0 	4294967294

Normally net masks are usually used: 255.255.255.0 255.255.255.0.0 255.0.0.0.0

And most commonly in our homes the 255.255.255.255.0.

In this way, and continuing with our example, the most logical thing is that our PC has:

	IP: 192.168.0.10
	Netmask: 255.255.255.255.0

Or with the ICDR notation:

	192.168.0.10/24

This way our device could communicate directly with any system in our network whose IP address started at 192.168.0.

If we have a device that belongs to the 192.168.1 subnet, it can no longer communicate directly and you should use a gateway, which we will see below.

On the other hand, if we want 192.168.0 and 192.168.1 networks to see each other directly, we could use the 255.255.0.0.0 network mask. In this case, you would really be looking at all the systems whose IPs start with 192.168, regardless of the next two blocks of numbers.

Gateway

When a system must send a data (package) to a network to which it does not belong, which it knows from its previously viewed network mask, it will search in its routing table for the ip address to which it must indicate this data so that it can be sent to the "outside". That is, if our PC wants to communicate with a system that is not in your network, you must know an IP to send this data, leaving the shipping control to that system.

In our example we know that the router has an IP address 192.168.0.1 for our internal network. We only have this network at home. Therefore, our default route or gateway should be the router address. Spoken in a colloquial way, if we send a packet to a system that is not on our network, let's send it to the router that he will know what to do with it. Internally the router when it receives the packet and sees the address to which it is destined, it will activate its mechanisms to send it through its public address abroad, contacting the external system.

DNS (Domain Name Server)

As mentioned above, all connected systems have an IP address. It would be very complicated if we could memorize all the IP addresses of all the pages we usually connect to. This is why there are servers that are capable of translating a name to an IP address (and vice versa). These servers are called DNS (Name Resolution Server).

Let's take as an example the navigation to a web page. When we write the name of a page in our browser, the system will first ask our DNS what is the IP address of the address we are requesting. Our DNS will return to our system an IP address that will correspond to the page we are requesting.

The "dig" tool allows us to check the ips addresses of a domain name.

	┌─[user@parrot]─[~]
	└──╼ $dig parrotsec.org
	
	; <<>> DiG 9.10.6-Debian <<>> parrotsec.org
	;; global options: +cmd
	;; Got answer:
	;; ->>HEADER<<- opcode: QUERY, status: NOERROR, id: 59479
	;; flags: qr rd ra; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 2, AUTHORITY: 0, 	ADDITIONAL: 1
	
	;; OPT PSEUDOSECTION:
	; EDNS: version: 0, flags:; udp: 4000
	;; QUESTION SECTION:
	;parrotsec.org.			IN	A
	
	;; ANSWER SECTION:
	parrotsec.org.		300	IN	A	104.24.125.114
	parrotsec.org.		300	IN	A	104.24.124.114
	
	;; Query time: 91 msec
	;; SERVER: 212.142.144.66#53(212.142.144.66)
	;; WHEN: Sun Nov 19 23:18:48 CET 2017
	;; MSG SIZE  rcvd: 74

You can see two important things in this example. The "ANSWER SECTION" section tells us the IP addresses of parrotsec.org and the SERVER line tells us which DNS server we asked for.

We can configure our systems with more than one DNS server, in case the main one fails.

DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol)

In the previous points we have defined several data that will be essential to configure our systems and that can be connected:

* IP Address
* Net Mask
* Gateway
* DNS
These values can be configured manually, but can also be set automatically when the system is connected to the network. These values can be supplied to us and configured by a DHCP server. Generally, routers come with this feature turned on so we don't have to worry about anything.

Final Note

Just as we have indicated at the beggining, this document is a brief (very brief) introduction to networks, and once you understand the basic operation of a network you should investigate and study its operation more extensively.

Below are links that may be of interest to you in the future:

	* https://rfc-es.org/
	* https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc-index.html
	* http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Networking-Overview-HOWTO.html